PERSONAL DETAILS

Email: dtopouza@gmail.com | danai.topouza@queensu.ca

Languages: English University of Cambridge Proficiency in English (May 2011), University of

Michigan Proficiency in English (May 2011), TOEFL iBT (Sept. 2012),

CELPIP General (Nov. 2018)

French DELF B1 Certification (May 2011)

Greek Native

PERSONAL STATEMENT

I am a research associate at the Computational Genomics Laboratory. I am interested in studying complex human traits using bioinformatics and data mining approaches. My previous work identified integrated gene expression networks, microRNA networks, and regulatory variants that are associated with poor response to adjuvant chemotherapy in ovarian cancer patients.

Practical skills:

Programming languages R, Python, Matlab, Linux (bash), git, Java, C

Bioinformatics NGS data analysis, microarray data analysis, genomics data analysis, multi-

omics data integration, bioinformatics databases, HPC environments,

molecular dynamics software

Machine learning Classification, clustering, pattern recognition algorithms

EDUCATION

Master of Science 2017 – 2019

Experimental Medicine, Specialization in Bioinformatics

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisor: Dr. Qingling Duan

Thesis: Integrated biological networks associated with platinum-based chemotherapy response in high-

grade serous ovarian cancer

Bachelor of Science (Honours)

2013 – 2017

Biology major, Computer Science minor Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisor: Dr. Paul G. Young

Thesis: Copper-induced stress response and programmed cell death in Saccharomyces cerevisiae

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Bioinformatics Research Associate

Jan. 2020 - Present

Computational Genomics Laboratory

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisor: Dr. Qingling Duan

Projects: DNA methylation analysis in hepatocellular carcinoma, RNA-seq analysis in chronic myeloid

leukemia, phenome-wide association studies (PheWAS) in the CHILD Study Cohort

Responsibilities: Contributing to literature review and analyses for grant applications, maintaining lab

server and website

MSc Candidate Sept. 2017 – Sept. 2019

Computational Genomics Laboratory

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisor: Dr. Qingling Duan

Project: Novel regulatory and transcriptomic networks associated with chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer

Undergraduate Research Thesis

Sept. 2016 - Apr. 2017

Department of Biology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisor: Dr. Paul G. Young

Project (BIOL 537, undergraduate 12-unit thesis): Characterizing transcriptomic changes during programmed cell death in S. cerevisiae

QGEM Dry Lab Executive

May 2016 - Oct. 2016

Queen's International Genetically Engineered Machine (iGEM) Team

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Head of the Dry Lab research team

Project: Modeling the non-ribosomal peptide synthetase adenylation domain and identifying mutations that alter amino acid binding specificity

Research Assistant Oct. 2015 – Jul. 2016

Department of Biology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

Supervisors: Dr. Tomas Babak (Queen's University, Kingston), Dr. Brian DeVeale (University of California, San Francisco)

Project: Statistical analysis and data visualization for a genome-wide association study on schizophrenia

Lab Assistant Internship

Jun. 2015 - Jul. 2015

IVF facility, Interbalkan Medical Center, Thessaloniki, Greece

Supervisor: Dr. Ioannis Tziafetas, MD

Responsibilities: Laboratory organization and maintenance

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Guest Lecturer 12, 18 Aug. 2020

Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

BMIF 803: Biomedical Data Mining and Applications, part of the Masters in Biomedical Informatics (MBI) diploma program

Teaching Assistant Sept. 2015 – Dec. 2018

Queen's University, Kingston, ON

BMED 370: Genetics and Genomics (Winter 2018, Fall 2018)

BIOL 102: Introductory Biology of Cells (Fall 2017)

CISC 101: Elements of Computer Science (Fall 2015, Fall 2016)

ACADEMIC MENTORSHIP

Helia Ghazinejad, Master of Biomedical Informatics Student, Ghasemlou Lab/Duan Lab (Sept. 2020 – Present). Project: *Identifying genes under circadian rhythm control in murine brain tissues*

Hanlin Chen, Master of Biomedical Informatics Student, Ghasemlou Lab/Duan Lab (Sept. 2020 – Present). Project: *Identifying microRNAs under circadian rhythm control in murine brain tissues*

Lisa Flaten, Master of Epidemiology, Peng Lab (May – Sept. 2020).

Project: Pre-processing and analysis of DNA methylation data for female shift workers

Sorin Park, Master of Biomedical Informatics Student, Duan Lab/Abraham Lab (Sept. – May 2018).

Project: Genes and co-expression networks associated with response to a novel combination treatment in chronic myeloid leukemia

PUBLICATIONS

Preprints

1. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Tarnouskaya A, Nicol CJB, Duan QL. Novel regulatory and transcriptional networks associated with resistance to platinum-based chemotherapy in ovarian cancer. *bioRxiv* (2020). doi:10.1101/2020.09.09.289868. *Under review in Gynecologic Oncology*.

Publications

1. Choi J, **Topouza DG**, Tarnouskay, A, Nesdoly S, Koti M, Duan QL. Gene networks and expression quantitative trait loci associated with adjuvant chemotherapy response in high-grade serous ovarian cancer. *BMC Cancer* 20, 413 (2020). PMID: 32404140

PUBLISHED ABSTRACTS

- 1. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Duan QL. Novel biological networks associated with chemotherapy response in high-grade serous ovarian cancer. *The 22nd Annual Scientific Meeting for Health Science Research Trainees* (2019).
- 2. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Duan QL. Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer; (Abstract #685). *The 68th Annual Meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics* (2018).
- 3. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Duan QL. Gene expression networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer. *The 3rd Annual Toronto RNA Enthusiast's Day* (2018).
- 4. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Duan QL. Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer. *The 21st Annual Scientific Meeting for Health Science Research Trainees* (2018).

POSTERS AND PRESENTATIONS

Oral presentations

- 1. **Conference Speaker.** Novel biological networks associated with chemotherapy response in high-grade serous ovarian cancer. *The 22nd Annual Scientific Meeting for Health Science Research, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queen's University* (4 Jun. 2019).
- 2. **Seminar Speaker.** Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer. *Masters Student Symposium Seminar Presentation, Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University* (26 Feb. 2019).
- 3. **Seminar Speaker.** A pharmacogenomics analysis of biological networks regulating chemotherapy response among ovarian cancer patients. *Masters Student Symposium Seminar Presentation, Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences, Queen's University* (24 Apr. 2018).
- 4. **Seminar Speaker.** Programmed cell death in the unicellular eukaryote *Saccharomyces cerevisiae*. *Undergraduate Thesis Seminar Presentation, Department of Biology, Queen's University* (11 Nov. 2016).

Poster presentations

- 1. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Duan QL. Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer; (Abstract #685). *American Society of Human Genetics Meeting, San Diego Convention Center, San Diego, CA* (16 20 Oct. 2018).
- 2. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Duan QL. Gene expression networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer. *Toronto RNA Enthusiast's Day (TREnD), Peter Gilgan Centre for Research and Learning, Toronto, ON* (31 Jul. 2018).
- 3. **Topouza DG**, Choi J, Nesdoly S, Duan QL. Biological networks modulating chemotherapy response in ovarian cancer. *The 21*st *Annual Scientific Meeting for Health Science Research, Faculty of Health Sciences, Queen's University, Kingston, ON* (13 Jun. 2018).
- 4. **Topouza DG**, Young PG. Programmed cell death in the unicellular eukaryote *Saccharomyces cerevisiae*. *Undergraduate Thesis Poster Presentations, Department of Biology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON* (10 Mar. 2017).
- 5. Nowak S, Thomsen C, **Topouza DG**. The role of mycorrhizal community assemblages in agricultural productivity. *Scinapse Undergraduate Science Case Competition (Finalist)*, *Western University, London, ON* (19 Mar. 2016).

AWARDS

Conference Travel Award (CTA)

Funding Agency: Queen's University, Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences. Amount: \$ 250 (CAD)

International Tuition Award (ITA)

2017 – 2018

Funding Agency: Queen's University, Department of Biomedical and Molecular Sciences. Amount: \$ 5,000 (CAD)

Queen' University Principal's Scholarship

2013 - 2014

Funding Agency: Queen's University. Amount: \$ 6,000 (CAD)

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

<u>Professional Extension</u>

MATH 136, MATH 235: Linear Algebra 1 and 2 (Audit)

Jan. – Apr. 2021

Online course, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, ON

KHSC/QU Innovation Workshop on Digital Health, Machine Learning, and AI 3 Feb. 2020

Donald Gordon Hotel and Conference Centre, Kingston, ON

Graduate Management Consulting Association (GMCA) mini-MBA Nov. 2017 – Dec. 2019

Queen's University, Kingston, ON

PATH 828: Bioinformatics for Cancer Research (Audit) 13 – 17 Mar. 2019

Richardson Laboratory, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

CISC 859: Pattern Recognition (Audit) Jan. – Apr. 2019

Goodwin Hall, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

ASHG/IGES/ISCB Joint Symposium: 16 Oct. 2018

Working with Big Data in the Cloud--Research and Privacy

San Diego Convention Center, San Diego, CA

HPC Summer School 2018: Bioinformatics Workflows 3 Aug. 2018

Chernoff Hall, Queen's University, Kingston, ON

The High Performance Computing Symposium (HPCS) 6 - 9 Jun. 2017

Queen's University, Kingston, Ontario

Professional Memberships

The American Society of Human Genetics 2018 - 2020